Finding Aid for the Townsend National Recovery Plan Records LSC.0219
UCLA Library Special Collections
Townsend National Recovery Plan records
1931-1961
UCLA Library Special Collections
Townsend National Recovery Plan, Inc.
LSC.0219
118.0 linear feet (230 boxes, 2 cartons, 1 oversize box, 1 map folder)
The Townsend Plan was proposed in 1933 by Francis Townsend. The plan called for a $200-a-month pension to any retired person over sixty. Bills to establish the Plan were brought up and defeated in Congress many times and the movement lost headway after passage of the Social Security Act in 1935. Boxes 1-145 include correspondence, minutes, bulletins, accounts, reports, directories, permit files, and miscellaneous records related to the Plan in the 12th Regional District (comprising the states of Arizona, Colorado, Nevada, and California).
Restrictions on Access
Portions of collection unprocessed. Materials in the collection are unavailable for access except for boxes 1-145. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942338793606533
Biography
The Townsend Plan was proposed in 1933 by Francis Townsend; it called for a $200-a-month pension to any retired person over sixty; it was to be paid in scrip and spent within a month; funds were to be raised by sales tax; bills to establish the Plan were brought up and defeated in Congress many times; the movement lost headway after passage of the Social Security Act, 1935.
Biographical Narrative
The Townsend Plan Incorporated was established in 1934 and incorported under the laws of the state of California by Dr. Francis Townsend and Robert E. Clements; the organization, with National Headquarters at Cleveland, Ohio, was divided into 12 regional districts; local organizations consisted of a district council for each Congressional District within the region.
Scope and Content
Boxes 1-145 include records related to the Townsend National Recovery Plan, Incorporated. 12th Regional District, comprising the states of Arizona, Colorado, Nevada, and California. Also includes correspondence, minutes, bulletins, accounts, reports, directories, and permit files.
Expanded Scope and Content
The Townsend Plan Incorporated was established in 1934 and incorporated under the laws of the State of California by Dr. Francis E. Townsend and Robert E. Clements. The Organization, with National Headquarters at Cleveland, Ohio, is divided into twelve regional districts corresponding to the Federal Reserve Districts of the United States Government.
The records described in this inventory are those of the 12th Regional District, comprising the states of Arizona, Colorado, Nevada, and California, with Regional Headquarters located at Modesto, California, under the direction of John C. Cuneo, National Representative and Secretary-Treasurer of the Townsend Plan Incorporated of California. The Regional District Headquarters supervises the activities of the local organization within the regional district. Local organizations consist of a district council for each Congressional District within the region, composed of representatives elected by officers of the local clubs. The local club, composed of members of the movement in good standing, is the smallest unit.
The records created by the 12th Regional District Headquarters contain two general files and five more or less specialized files, including financial records, and cover the period 1938 to 1952. The records of the Regional Headquarters prior to 1938 have been destroyed. The first general file contains correspondence, copies of minutes of local club meetings, bulletins of local clubs, reports, and copies of receipts for contributions received by the Regional Headquarters. The file is arranged chronologically and alphabetically thereunder in two separate catagories: (1) Individuals file (2) Clubs file. The second file contains the same type of material as the first, but relates only to the business of the Townsend Party in California from 1940 to 1944, and is arranged in the same manner as the first file. The specialized files consist of the minutes and correspondence of the California State Advisory Committee and Council, organizations created within the Regional District to promote social welfare legislation; a Speakers' Permit file containing applications for speakers' permits from members of the movement in the 12th Regional District; a file of Townsend Club Officers in the Regional District; bulletins issued by the Regional Headquarters, and financial records.
The records described in this inventory constitute all the extant records of the Townsend Plan Incorporated, 12th Regional District Headquarters, except for the current files which are located at the Headquarters Office in Modesto, California. They amount to 54 linear feet. Records pertaining to other aspects of the Townsend Plan Incorporated in the 12th Regional District are in the possession of the local clubs, the National Headquarters at Cleveland, Ohio, and in the Personal File of John C. Cuneo located in the Department of Special Collections at the Library of the University of California, Los Angeles.
Related Material
The Townsend Plan in retrospect [oral history transcript] / John C. Cuneo, interviewee. UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research interview, 1970. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Business records.; Old age pensions -- United States -- Archives.; Townsend National Recovery Plan, Inc.--Archives.
- General File, September 1, 1939-August 21, 1952; 40 ft.
  Scope and Contents note
  Copies of letters sent and letters received by the Regional Headquarters of the 12th District from varioius officials and members of the organization, pertaining to business and policy and including questions from individuals concerning the Townsend Plan; copies of receipts for contributions, minutes and bulletins of local clubs, reports and correspondence relating to the Ham and Eggs Plan arranged chronologically and alphabetically as received thereunder as follows:
  - Individuals, 1940-1952
    - September 1, 1939-February 12, 1940. (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
    - June 1, 1941-January 1, 1942. (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9)
    - January 1-July 9, 1942. (Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
    - July 10, 1942-March 1943. (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
    - April 1943-December 1944. (Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27)
    - January-June 1944. (Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37)
    - June-December 1944. (Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47)
    - January-August 1945. (Box 52, Box 53)
    - August 1945-February 1946. (Box 58, Box 59)
    - February 1946-March 1947. (Box 63, Box 64, Box 65, Box 66)
    - March-September 1947. (Box 71, Box 72, Box 73, Box 74)
    - September 1947-July 26, 1948. (Box 77, Box 78, Box 79)
    - July 1948-September 8, 1949. (Box 80, Box 81, Box 82)
    - September 7, 1949-December 1950. (Box 83, Box 84, Box 85, Box 86)
    - January 1951-November 20, 1951. (Box 89, Box 90, Box 91)
    - November 20, 1951-August 21, 1952. (Box 93, Box 94, Box 95)
  - Clubs, 1942-1959
    - January 1-July 9, 1942. (Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16)
    - July 10, 1942-March 1943. (Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23)
    - April 1943-December 1944. (Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32)
    - January-June 1944. (Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41)
    - June-December 1944. (Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51)
    - January-August 1945. (Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box 57)
    - August 1945-February 1946. (Box 60, Box 61, Box 62)
    - February 1946-March 1947. (Box 67, Box 68, Box 69, Box 70)
    - September 1947-July 26, 1948. (Box 75, Box 76)
    - July 1948-September 8, 1949. (Box 83)
    - September 7, 1949-December 1950. (Box 87, Box 88)
    - January 1951-November 20, 1951. (Box 92)
    - November 20, 1951-August 21, 1952. (Box 96, Box 97)
    - 1952-1959. (Box 98, Box 99, Box 100, Box 101, Box 102)
      General note
      Files for the dates not covered in the above list have been destroyed.
- Townsend Party File, February 10, 1940-September 27, 1944.; 3 ft. (Box 103, Box 104, Box 105, Box 106, Box 107, Box 108, Box 109)
  Copies of letters sent and letters received by John C. Cuneo, Secretary of the Townsend Party of California, during most of the period when the Party was officially on the ballot of the State of California pertaining to the formulation of party policy, support and business; arranged alphabetically as received in two alphabetical files as follows: Individual members file, box 1-3 and Club file.
- Minutes of the State Advisory Council of California, 1938-1946.; 1 ft. (Box 110)
  Handwritten, typewritten and mimeographed minutes arranged chronologically.
- Townsend Club Officers' Directories, 1939-1950 and 1951-1961.; 3 ft. (Box 111, Box 112, Box 113, Box 114, Box 115, Box 116, Box 117, Box 118, Box 119, Box 120)
  Original typewritten copies of reports received from officers of the Townsend Clubs in the 12th Regional District listing personnel elected to the club and district councils, meeting place and number of paid up members; arranged chronologically and numerically by congressional district thereunder; district council directories are filed at the beginning of each district but are occasionally missing because district council members are chosen from club council members within each district and distict elections are not always held before yearly reports are submitted.
  Directories for 1944-1947 are missing.
- Townsend State Advisory Committee File, December 8, 1939-November 2, 1940.; 3 ft. (Box 121, Box 122, Box 123, Box 124, Box 125, Box 126, Box 127)
  Copies of letters sent and letters received by John C. Cuneo from various persons and from members of the Townsend State Legislative Advisory Committee pertaining to the efforts of the Committee to advance social welfare legislation in California; includes receipts for contributions and invoices for expenses of the Committee; arranged alphabetically as received; receipts and invoices filed in envelopes at the end of the file.
- Speakers' Permit File, 1938-1948.; 5 in. (Box 128)
  Applications received from various members of the Townsend Plan movement to speak at rallys and meetings in behalf of the movement; including copies of letters received and letters sent by John C. Cuneo pertaining to speakers' permits; arranged chronologically in folders, but filed in reverse chronological order within individual folders.
- Bulletins, 1938-1952 and 1952-1961.; 1 ft. (Box 129, Box 130, Box 131)
  Mimeographed notices and bulletins issued to clubs and council members of the 12th Regional District by John C. Cuneo; arranged chronologically in folders, but filed in reverse chronological order within individual folders.
- Accounts, 1938-1951.; 2 ft. (Box 132, Box 133, Box 134, Box 135, Box 136, Box 137)
  Receipts, disbursements, general ledgers and financial records of contributions received by the 12th Regional District Headquarters from members and clubs within the District; arranged as follows:
  - Townsend Plan Incorporated, 12th Regional District (Modesto Office). (Box 132, Box 133, Box 134, Box 135, Box 136, Box 137)
    - Disbursements and general ledger, November 1, 1940-January 7, 1948. (Box 132)
    - Accounts payable, November 1, 1940-January 7, 1948. (Box 133)
  - Townsend Party of California. (Box 134)
    - Accounts, 1938-1941. (Box 134)
  - Townsend State Advisory Committee. (Box 135)
    - Receipts and disbursements and general ledger, December 8, 1939-November 2, 1940. (Box 135)
  - Townsend State Legislative Committee. (Box 136)
    - Receipts, disbursements and general ledger, November 7, 1947-December 3, 1951. (Box 136)
  - Townsend state office accounts, 1946-1956. (Box 137)
  - Townsend Club no.2, Modesto
    - Records
      - Minutes, Financial Records, 1945-1956. (Box 138)
      - Membership Rosters, Financial Records, 1945-1956. (Box 139)
- Townsend Plan, Los Angeles Office
  - Miscellaneous Records Correspondence. (Box 140, Box 141, Box 142, Box 143)
    - Vitamin Sale Records. (Box 144)
    - National convention; Field employees manual; speakers manual., 1945 (Box 145)
- Series 11. (Box 146, Box 147)
- Series 12. (Box 148, Box 149, Box 150, Box 151, Box 152, Box 153, Box 154, Box 155, Box 156, Box 157, Box 158, Box 159, Box 160, Box 161, Box 162, Box 163, Box 164, Box 165, Box 166, Box 167, Box 168, Box 169, Box 170, Box 171, Box 172, Box 173, Box 174, Box 175, Box 176, Box 177, Box 178, Box 179, Box 180, Box 181, Box 182, Box 183, Box 184, Box 185, Box 186, Box 187, Box 188, Box 189, Box 190, Box 191, Box 192, Box 193, Box 194, Box 195, Box 196, Box 197, Box 198, Box 199, Box 200, Box 201, Box 202, Box 203, Box 204, Box 205, Box 206, Box 207, Box 208, Box 209, Box 210, Box 211, Box 212, Box 213, Box 214, Box 215, Box 216, Box 217, Box 218, Box 219, Box 220, Box 221, Box 222, Box 223, Box 224, Box 225, Box 226, Box 227, Box 228, Box 229, Box 230)
- Series 12. (Carton 231, Carton 232)
- Townsend National Weekly Photographs, Banner, Miscellaneous. (Box 233)
- 14th Townsend National Convention Panorama, June 7-10, 1954 (Box 234)